A Guide to the Research Papers of Joseph Medard Carriere and of John Cook Wyllie, 1831(1935-1974) and n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Research Papers of Joseph Medard Carriere and of John Cook Wyllie, 1831(1935-1974) and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8880-l
This collection consists of ca. 710 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 710 items, ca. 1831(1935-1974) and n.d., of typed manuscripts and research materials compiled by Joseph Medard Carriere (1902-1970), professor of Romance Languages at the University of Virginia, on French history and of research materials compiled by John Cook Wyllie (1908-1968) on printing and Virginia history. Among the correspondence of Carriere are letters and enclosures from William E. Rachel, editor of the Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, and Charles E. Hatch, Jr., historian of Colonial National Historical Park, concerning aspects of French history; there is also a letter from Lucretia Bishko to William Runge concerning Carriere's manuscript on the Virginia Campaign of 1781. There are various typed versions with handwritten notes and revisions of "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781," translated and edited by Carriere. Wyllie compiled research materials on various aspects of printing such as engravings, printers, presses, typography, and watermarks as well as on Virginia history and miscellaneous subjects. The miscellaneous material includes a newspaper article, 1939, concerning the McGregor Library with a photograph of John Cook Wyllie among others.
Contents List
- Research Papers of Joseph Medard Carriere
  - Correspondence of Joseph Medard Carriere 1958-1974 (Box 1)
  - "Brissot de Marville's Plea for the Creation of an American Language" n.d. (Box 1)
  - "Early Examples of the Expression of 'American Language'" n.d. (Box 1)
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" n.d., Pages 1-4; 18-59 (Box 1)
    Introduction and Notes
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" n.d., Pages 19-92 (Box 1)
    Notes
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" n.d., Pages 21-53 (Box 1)
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" n.d., Pages 1-92 (Box 1)
    Text and Notes
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" n.d., Pages 1-59 (Box 1)
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" n.d., Pages 1-46 (Box 1)
  - "A French Diary of the Virginia Campaign of 1781" 1958, Pages 1-41 (Box 1)
  - "Unpublished Comments of William Short on Mme. d' Houdetot" n.d. (Box 1)
- Research Papers of John Cook Wyllie
  - Engravings 1831 (Box 2)
    A New Family Encyclopedia pages
  - Engravings n.d. (Box 2)
    Woodblocks reoccurring in same book
  - Engravings n.d. (Box 2)
    Woodblocks used in the Virginia Gazette, 1755-1774
  - Library of Thomas Jefferson 1957, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Margaret and John of London Sea Flight n.d. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1939, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
  - Printers 1935, n.d. (Box 2)
    Edward Allde (fl. 1587-1621)
  - Printers 1961, n.d. (Box 2)
    John Allen
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
    William Caxton (ca. 1422-1491)
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
    G. Eld
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
    Henry Hammond (1605-1660)
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
    Iohn Iaggard versions of the Essaies of Sr. Francis Bacon.. ., 1606, 1612, and 1613
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
    Felix Kingston
  - Printers n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
    Valentine Simmes
  - Printers n.d. (Box 2)
    George Veseler and Nathaniel Butter versions of... A Wonderful Sea Fight.. ., 1621
  - Printer's Devices n.d. (Box 2)
  - Printer's Signatures or Quire Marks 1954-1959, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Printing Presses 1961, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Typography 1961-1963, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Watermarks 1963, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Margaret and John of London Sea Fight n.d. (Oversize P-20)
  - Copies of Miscellaneous Virginiana from the University of Virginia Library and the Virginia State Library 1950, n.d. (Oversize P-20)
    Materials relating to Edmund Randolph, Thomas Jefferson, and Walker Timberlake